Guide to the Archives of the Soviet communist party and Soviet state microfilm collection: Russian State Archives of Social and Political History (Rossiiskii gosudarstvennyi arkhiv sotsialno-politicheskoi istorii - RGASPI)
Hoover Institution Archives
- Fond 572, Records of the Central Auditing Commission of the RKP(b)-KPSS, 1921-1925, 1944-1950; 4 reels (Reel 2.533-2.536)
  The Central Auditing Commission was elected by party congresses. It controlled and audited financial, organizational, and economic activities and the condition of administrative work in the party.
  Fond 572 consists of two opis and contains documents related to the activities of the Central Auditing Commission of the TsK KPSS, 1921-1925 and 1944-1950. The material covers the preparation of TsK RKP(b) reports at the Eleventh, Twelfth, and Fourteenth party congresses; reports relating to the work of various TsK departments; reports regarding investigations and purges of party members; comparative data on the situation in party organization before the Tenth, Eleventh, and Twelfth RKP(b)congresses; decisions made by the Central Auditing Commission regarding the operation of the central party institutions before the Twelfth and Fourteenth congresses, with related materials; minutes of the meetings, reports, and auditing documents of local auditing commissions; information on party conferences in gubernias and on the ethical situation and party work within local party organizations, along with the evaluation of their work made by the TsK RKP(b).
  Documents in opisi 1-2 are available on microfilm at the Hoover Archives. A Russian-language finding aid is on microfilm reel number 2.52. A microfilm reel list, which provides opis number, delo number, and corresponding microfilm reel number, is available in the reading room of the Hoover Institution Archives.
- Fond 582, Records of the Twenty Fourth Congress of the KPSS, 1971; 2 reels (Reel 2.537-2.538)
  The Twenty Fourth Congress of the KPSS was held in Moscow in March-April 1971. Fond 582 contains one opis consisting of sixteen printed brochures with protocols and verbatim records of plenary and sectional meetings of the Twenty Fourth Congress and greetings to the Congress.
- Fond 586, Collection of Documents for Development of the Third Program of the KPSS, 1958-1961; 33 reels (Reel 2.539-2.571)
  Development of the Third KPSS Program started per resolution of the Twentieth Congress of the KPSS (February 1956). The theoretical and political part of the Program was developed mainly by a working group, established in the summer of 1958 under the aegis of the TsK KPSS International Department. Scholars from different areas of expertise participated in this project. The draft program was placed under the consideration of a joint meeting of the TsK KPSS Presidium and the Program Commission; on June 19, 1961, it was presented for consideration to the TsK KPSS Plenum, and then it was published and opened for public discussion. The Program was adopted by the Twenty Second KPSS Congress in October 1961.
  Fond 586 consists of one opis including draft resolutions, letters, work schedules, draft versions of different parts of the program, comments, amendments, a register of classified documents checked out by the authors of the program, etc.
- Fond 592, Records of the Nineteenth Congress of the KPSS, 1952; 13 reels (Reel 2.2590-2.2602)
  The Nineteenth Congress of the KPSS was held in Moscow in October 1952.
  Special attention should be paid to Fond 592. The Russian finding aid states that there is one file (delo ) in this Fond, containing 16 printed brochures with protocols and verbatim records of the meetings of the 19th Congress. It turned out that opis 1 contains 113 files consisting of actual documents, of which only the last one contains those 16 printed brochures with protocols and verbatim records. In fact, this collection contains all kinds of documents related to the preparation for, summoning, and convening of the 19th congress and to its results, such as resolutions of the Politburo and TsK VKP(b) plenums; draft opening and closing speeches; materials relating to the invitations sent to foreign communist parties and foreign journalists; several versions of the reports of G. M. Malenkov (Secretary of the TsK VKP(b)), of M. Z. Saburov (Chairman of the State Committee for Planning) about the 1951-1955 five year plan, and of N. S. Khrushchev about amendments to the VKP(b) Code, with handwritten corrections made by the authors, I. V. Stalin, and other Politburo members; Stalin's speech, etc. Verbatim records of the meetings of the Congress are presented in the following versions: unedited, edited by responsible officials, edited by the editorial commission of the Congress, and information for press and radio, with signatures of party leaders, amendments and corrections. Other documents included in this opis are statements about appeals sent to the Congress, voting certificates of every delegate to the Congress; a register for temporary identification cards given to the delegates; and other documents.
  Documents in opis 1 are available on microfilm at the Hoover Archives. A Russian-language finding aid is on microfilm reel number 2.53, but it is inadequate. No microfilm reel list is available.
- Fond 593, Records of the Twenty Third Congress of the KPSS, 1966; 1 reel (Reel 2.572)
  The Twenty Third Congress of the KPSS took place in Moscow in April 1966. Fond 593 contains one opis consisting of sixteen printed brochures with minutes and verbatim records of plenary and sectional meetings of the Twenty Third Congress.
  Documents in opis 1 are available on microfilm at the Hoover Archives. A Russian-language finding aid is on microfilm reel number 2.53. A microfilm reel list, which provides opis number, delo number, and corresponding microfilm reel number, is available in the reading room of the Hoover Institution Archives.
- Fond 604, Records Twenty Fifth Congress of the KPSS, 1976; 4 reels (Reel 2.573-2.576)
  The Twenty Fifth Congress of the KPSS was held in Moscow in February-March 1976. Fond 604 contains one opis consisting of printed brochures with minutes and verbatim records of plenary and sectional meetings of the Twenty Fifth Congress.
- Fond 620, Records of the Twenty Sixth Congress of the KPSS, 1981; 3 reels (Reel 2.577-2.579)
  The Twenty Sixth Congress of the KPSS took place in Moscow in 1981. Fond 620 contains one opis including agenda and procedures and regulations of the Congress; report of the TsK KPSS to the Twenty Sixth Congress delivered by L. I. Brezhnev (printed); fourteen printed brochures with protocols and verbatim records of plenary and sectional meetings of the Twenty Sixth Congress; Osnovnye napravleniia ekonomicheskogo i sotsial'nogo razvitiia SSSR na 1981-1985 gg. i na period do 1990(Main Directions of Economic and Social Development of the USSR for the Years from 1981 to 1985 and through the year 1990); report by N. A.Tikhonov; information on the arrival of foreign communist, workers', and national-democratic parties to the Congress; greetings to the Congress from foreign parties and organizations; and other documents.
  Documents in opis 1 are available on microfilm at the Hoover Archives. A Russian-language finding aid is on microfilm reel number 2.55. A microfilm reel list, which provides opis number, delo number, and corresponding microfilm reel number, is available in the reading room of the Hoover Institution Archives.
- Fond 628, Records of the Twenty Seventh Congress of the KPSS, 1986; 1 reel (Reel 2.580)
  The Twenty Seventh Congress of the KPSS was held in Moscow in February-March 1986. Fond 628 contains one opis consisting of printed brochures with protocols and verbatim records of plenary and sectional meetings of the Twenty Seventh Congress.
- Fond 646, Records of the Twenty Eighth Congress of the KPSS, 1990; 2 reels (Reel 2.581-2.582)
  The Twenty Eighth Congress of the KPSSC took place in Moscow in 1990. Fond 628 contains one opis consisting of printed brochures with protocols and verbatim records of plenary and sectional meetings of the Twenty Eighth Congress.